On the 26th of August 1346, south of the
port town of Calais in northern France,
an outnumbered English army commanded by King
Edward III of England confronted the forces of
King Philip VI of France. As the fighting raged,
the English right flank was furiously assaulted
by the French. Despite the immense odds and after
being thrown to the ground and nearly losing his
life in the fighting, it was the 16-year old son
of the English king, Prince Edward, who rallied
their forces and beat back the French. Victory at
the Battle of Crécy was only the beginning of the
remarkable career of Prince Edward. Who was he,
how did he contribute to the Hundred Years’ War
and why did he never become King of England? This
is the story of Edward, the Black Prince.
The man known to history as Edward of Woodstock,
or Edward the Black Prince, was born on the 15th
of June 1330 at Woodstock Palace in Oxfordshire
in England. The origins of the name ‘The Black
Prince’ are not known for certain. Prince Edward
was not called by this name when he was alive.
Rather it was adopted during the Tudor era, over
a hundred years after his death. Some speculate
that the name arises from the black armour he
was said to have habitually worn into battle,
whilst others claim that it was derived from
the dark reputation he garnered by engaging
in scorched earth campaigns or chevauchées
across France during the Hundred Years’ War.
A third theory is that this name comes from
his coat of arms, which depicted three ostrich
feathers set against a black background.
The Black Prince’s father was King Edward III of
England, the son and heir of King Edward II.
Edward III became king in 1327 at the age of
fourteen after his weak and unpopular father was
deposed by his wife Isabella and her lover, Roger
Mortimer, a powerful English noble who along with
Isabella organised an uprising while in France
and invaded England in 1326, rapidly supplanting
Edward’s government. Edward II’s great mistake was
to grant excessive power throughout his reign to a
series of court favourites such as Piers Gaveston
and the Despenser family, actions which ultimately
cost him his throne and his life in 1327. The
Black Prince’s mother was Phillipa of Hainault,
the daughter of William I, Count of Hainault. She
was Queen of England from the date of her marriage
to Edward III on the 24th of January 1328 until
her death on the 15th of August 1369. Edward and
Phillipa would ultimately have thirteen children
of whom Prince Edward was the eldest.
When Edward was born in the summer of 1330,
his father was still basically a puppet of
his mother and Mortimer. They had managed to
overthrow the unpopular Edward II in 1327 and then
seized control of England, with Isabella’s teenage
son being king in name only at first. However,
Edward III soon showed that he was nothing like
his father in terms of his political and military
abilities. It was the birth of his son and heir,
Edward of Woodstock, that galvanised the King to
move against the increasingly unpopular Mortimer
and Isabella. On the 19th of October 1330, Edward
III raided a castle where the couple were residing
in Nottingham and captured them. On the 29th of
November Mortimer was executed, while Isabella was
placed under house confinement and banned from all
political activity. Edward’s decisive reassertion
of royal power was welcomed by the English
nobility. The young king immediately resolved to
wage war on the Scots to avenge the humiliation of
the Battle of Bannockburn in 1314, through which
Edward II had lost control over Scotland. Edward
III’s well-trained army secured a complete victory
over the Scottish forces at the Battle of Halidon
Hill on the 19th of July 1333. Edward was received
as a hero on his return to England. Thereafter
he was determined to rebuild England’s might as
it had existed in the time of his grandfather,
King Edward I, or indeed in the days of King
Henry II in the twelfth century when the English
king had ruled over most of northern and western
France as well. In this task of royal renewal, his
eldest son would become an able participant.
Details of the early life of Edward of Woodstock
are scarce. He was made the Earl of Chester in
1333, his first title, and was brought up in
the surroundings of a magnificent court, where
feasting and celebration were abundant. The young
prince was dressed in fine silk clothes and given
a personal tailor. However, the prince’s father
also wanted to ensure that his heir could perform
his duties as a military ruler as well one day.
To this end, the Prince received his first suit
of armour at the age of 7, and from the age of 13
participated in the numerous chivalric tournaments
held by the King. The first decade of his reign
saw Edward III embroiled in further conflict with
the Scottish King, David II, leading multiple
campaigns in the Scottish borderlands following
Halidon Hill. However, his thoughts soon turned
towards England’s greatest enemy, France, and
in 1337 Edward launched what would become known
as the Hundred Years’ War, the conflict in which
the Black Prince would establish himself as one of
the great military leaders of the medieval period.
Edward’s claim to the French throne originated
from the death in 1328 of King Charles IV of
France without a male heir, leaving two chief
claimants for the throne: Philip, Count of Valois,
Edward’s cousin, and Edward himself, whose
mother Isabella was Charles’ sister. The French
aristocracy chose Philip of Valois to become
Philip VI of France. This choice was not contested
at first, primarily because at the time Isabella
and Mortimer wanted to maintain good relations
with the French. Indeed, even when Edward
took personal control of England late in 1330,
he maintained cordial relations with Philip
as he dealt first with the Scots in the years
that followed. But relations between the English
and French monarchs soured gradually and in 1337
England went to war with France after Philip
threatened to confiscate the Duchy of Gascony,
England’s last major holding on the continent.
At first Edward went to war exclusively over
the Gascony issue, but early in 1340 Edward
extended the cause for war by publicly asserting
his claim to the French crown. Thus, the war
that would rage on and off down to 1453 was
over England’s right to the French throne,
but also the effort to reclaim territories
like the Duchy of Normandy that England had
lost back in the early thirteenth century.
Edward’s initial plan in the war was to draw
the French forces into a decisive battle. Thus,
he invaded northern France in the autumn of 1339,
using scorched earth tactics to devastate the
countryside. However, King Philip refused to meet
the English in open battle and withdrew his forces
into defensive positions, forcing Edward back
to Flanders without a victory. It was there that
he formally declared his claim to the French
throne in January 1340 in the city of Ghent.
By then Edward was desperate for a victory over
the French, as heavy taxation at home in England
to pay for his army was unpopular. He therefore
assembled more than 100 ships at Holbrook in the
East of England to ferry his troops to Flanders
and began a new offensive with his Flemish allies.
Yet the French had anticipated this move and
were blockading his entry into Flanders with
a fleet twice as large as his own. Edward received
news of this, but nonetheless chose to sail on the
22nd of June. The fleets clashed two days later
near the town of Sluys. Though the French boats
were faster, their sailors were inexperienced in
combat, while Edward’s vessels were crammed with
skilled archers. Furthermore, the French boats
were bound together to maintain a defensive
position, making the fleet extremely immobile.
The English consequently won a total victory,
capturing almost the entire French fleet. Despite
the stunning naval success at the Battle of Sluys,
Edward could still not force King
Philip into a decisive battle on
French territory. He soon ran out of funds
and was forced to abandon his campaign.
After peace talks in 1344 ended in failure,
Edward launched a major new campaign in 1346.
By now the Black Prince was 16 years old and
considered to be old enough to take part in
the war. He had also been made the Prince of
Wales in 1343. Father and son, with their army,
landed in Normandy on the 12th of July 1346 with
a 14,000-strong army. Upon their arrival there,
the Prince was knighted by his father and
given command of the vanguard of the army.
After pillaging the town of Caen in late July,
with the Black Prince playing a leading role in
the town’s capture, Edward’s army continued its
easterly march through Normandy towards Calais.
After crossing the River Somme on the 24th of
August they arrived on a ridge of high ground
between the villages of Crecy and Wadicourt.
The English king had around 2,500 men-at-arms,
3,000 cavalry, 2,000 spearmen and 5,000 to 7,000
longbowmen, whilst a swiftly approaching French
force was much larger, numbering over 20,000 men.
However, the English were well-rested when the
battle commenced on the 26th, whereas the French
were tired after a long march northwards. While
King Edward commanded the centre of the army
and the Earl of Northampton the left, the Black
Prince was given command of the right wing. The
French advance was led by Genoese crossbowmen,
with the extensive French cavalry building up
behind them. Seeing the Genoese falter under
heavy English longbow fire, they charged
through the crossbowmen, causing chaos and
confusion in the French ranks. While this slowed
the French onslaught, in the early evening the
main French force arrived on the battlefield
and charged the English right under the Black
Prince. This led to a severe struggle, in which
the Prince himself was beaten to the ground.
However, reinforcements from the English left
helped repel the French attack, and Prince Edward,
though badly concussed, soon picked himself up and
continued fighting valiantly. As daylight faded,
the French launched wave after wave of cavalry
attacks to no avail. King Philip himself had two
horses slain under him during the battle and
received an arrow wound in his face. As night
fell, with his army disintegrating around
him against a steady English advance, he
reluctantly fled the field, conceding a terrible
defeat to King Edward’s triumphant army.
The Battle of Crecy was one of the greatest
English victories of the Hundred Years’ War,
with Edward’s army sustaining fewer than 300
casualties, while the French casualties were
far higher, including a great number of prominent
nobles, such as Philip’s brother, the Count of
Alencon and King John of Bohemia. The Black Prince
and his father came across the body of King John
when surveying the battlefield the following day.
They were deeply moved, for John was one of the
foremost warriors of his age, losing his sight
whilst on crusade. It is said that the Prince took
John’s emblem of three white feathers and made it
his own. John’s emblem remains the symbol of the
Prince of Wales to this day. Following the battle,
Edward laid siege to the port of Calais, whilst an
invading Scottish army, encouraged by Philip to
exploit Edward’s absence, was decisively defeated
at Neville’s Cross by an English force under the
Archbishop of York on the 17th of October 1346.
Calais finally surrendered in August 1347 and
in October of that year, King Edward negotiated
a truce and returned to London.
The spirit of jubilation across England
surrounding Edward and his son’s great victories
was quickly brought to an end, when in August 1348
the Black Death crossed the English Channel
and ravaged the country. The bubonic plague
would eventually kill over one-third of Europe’s
population. Densely populated cities like London
were particularly badly hit. Indeed, the Black
Prince was personally impacted by the disease,
as it claimed the life of his sister Joan on
the 2nd of September 1348. Nevertheless, in
spite of the plague, King Edward inaugurated a new
chivalric order at Windsor Castle that same year,
naming it the Order of the Garter. It had 26
original members including the Black Prince,
who had assisted his father in selecting the
other founding members, all of whom were selected
based on acts of valour, rather than simply
their rank. The Order was arguably the most
enduring legacy of King Edward III’s reign, as
it remains the most senior order of knights in
the United Kingdom to this day. As the effects of
the plague began to dissipate in late 1349, King
Edward saw the chance to reclaim the offensive
against France. After hearing of an imminent
attempt to recapture Calais, the king and his
son went to the vital port ahead of the French,
and sprung a trap on their enemy, repulsing
the French force on the 1st of January 1350,
although not without the Black Prince having to
lead his garrison in saving his father, after
Edward became stranded outside the city gates,
against a much larger enemy force.
The Black Prince owned large estates
throughout England. He implemented a host
of revenue-generating policies when his income
fell after the Black Death. During the crisis he
showed himself to be a fair landlord, instructing
his revenue official in Cornwall in 1351, to ‘deal
equitably and rightly’ with his tenants and to
protect them from ‘oppressions and extortions’.
Furthermore, after local unrest in Cheshire
in the summer of 1353, the Prince travelled
to the county himself, holding judicial
sessions to settle grievances. He also
agreed to grant Cheshire a charter of liberties.
This successful management of his lands aside,
the Black Prince was also gaining a
reputation as an overly indulgent spender,
constantly living beyond his financial means to
fund his extravagant lifestyle. This being said,
it should be noted that the Prince’s extravagance
was not mindless spending. In medieval England
great lords needed to be generous in feasting and
gift-giving to recruit men into their service and
maintain their allegiance. Striking a balance
between rewarding one’s followers and avoiding
the burden of debt was a challenge faced by many
medieval lords, especially after the Black Death
when there were labour shortages all across
the continent and soldiers and farmers were
in an excellent negotiating position when it
came to the retention of their services.
In 1355, Jean de Grailly, a knight of the
garter from Gascony, the English-held province
in south-western France, informed King Edward
that people in the region were concerned with
the actions of the Count of Armagnac, who had been
appointed by King John II of France as governor
of the southern region of Languedoc, and who had
captured a number of Gascon towns and fortresses.
Edward was keen to resume the offensive against
France and his Great Council decided that the
Black Prince should lead an expedition from
Gascony to secure the province and punish the
Count of Armagnac. Furthermore, on the 10th of
July the Prince was made the King’s lieutenant
in Gascony, allowing him to basically govern
Gascony as a de-facto royal viceroy. He was
given an army of 2,600 men, to be bolstered by
Gascon soldiers. Accompanying the Prince to France
were fourteen knights of the Garter, including the
experienced Earls of Warwick and Suffolk and the
Prince’s special advisers and close friends,
Sir John Chandos and Sir James Audley. They
reached Bordeaux on the 20th of September 1355.
The following day a religious ceremony was held
in Saint-Andre Cathedral, after which the Prince
spoke directly to the inhabitants of Bordeaux,
telling them of his plan to take the offensive
against the Languedoc governor, by marching east
and ravaging his lands in a great chevauchée,
a French term meaning a brutal plundering raid,
where land either side of the advancing column
was burned. The aim of a chevauchée was to plunder
the wealth and resources of the enemy’s land in
order to undermine the enemy’s capacity to wage
war. With the Gascon contingents joining his army,
the Black Prince’s force reached around 8,000 men,
and on the 5th October they set off from Bordeaux
following the river Garonne, and entering
Armagnac’s lands on the 12th of October, where
the troops began burning, and fires soon raged for
many miles around the army. Though Armagnac was in
command of a larger force than the Anglo-Gascons,
he did not want to risk battle against the
Black Prince’s experienced men. Instead,
he gathered his army in the fortified city of
Toulouse and destroyed the bridges over the
Garonne and Ariege rivers, hoping the raid would
fizzle out or come to a halt before the rivers.
On the 28th of October the Prince reached the
Garonne south of Toulouse. The Prince had been
informed by local guides in his service that
the stream could be forded. As such, he led his
army across the river. This audacious move greatly
boosted the morale of his men, while causing panic
amongst Armagnac and the French, who assumed the
Prince would turn back before the rivers. Instead,
his army now marched east through the Languedoc,
a region totally unprepared for the carnage that
bore down upon them. The army reached the
major town of Carcassonne and razed its
outer settlements to the ground on the 6th of
November, and then continued on to Narbonne,
which was occupied on the 8th of November. The
Prince’s troops had now covered 250 miles since
leaving Bordeaux and were within sight of the
Mediterranean Sea. Edward ultimately decided to
return to Gascony before the winter weather set
in. The Prince’s army re-crossed the Garonne on
the 20th of November, and after receiving
reinforcements, the Count of Armagnac finally
left Toulouse. He shadowed the Anglo-Gascons as
they marched west, much to the fury of John II,
the French King. On the 28th of November,
the Prince arrived back on Gascon soil,
and spent Christmas at Bordeaux amid great
rejoicing and celebration, for the expedition
had been a clear success. Many Gascon lords who
had joined the French, now rallied to the English
cause, as Armagnac’s failure to protect his
vassal’s lands, had been brutally exposed.
The chevauchée of 1355 further demonstrated the
Black Prince’s military skill. As news of its
success arrived to England, Edward III sensed
an opportunity to launch a wider offensive
against his enemy, as King John II was facing a
crisis in his relations with the French nobility,
originating from John’s arrest of the powerful
aristocrat Charles of Navarre and other Norman
lords at a dinner party in Rouen, when he threw
Charles in jail and executed four nobles, causing
Normandy to rise in revolt against the French
King. To exploit this situation, King Edward
sent a small force under the Duke of Lancaster to
Normandy at the beginning of June 1356 and urged
the Black Prince to march north to link up with
Lancaster’s army, in order to attack John II’s
son, the Count of Poitiers, who was charged with
the defence of France south of the Loire River.
The Prince was delayed in his expedition by a
resurgent Count of Armagnac, whose incursions
into Gascony forced the Prince to leave 2,000 of
his 8,000-strong force in the duchy to defend it
before he began his march on the 4th of August,
moving north through France and devastating the
lands as they went. As the Prince neared the Loire
River, he began to realise the serious danger his
army was in, as Lancaster had ended his Normandy
campaign in the face of a larger French force,
whilst John II was building an immense army at
Chartres. Moreover, while John remained unpopular
with the French aristocracy, they now rallied
to him out of fear of the Black Prince. Thus,
the king was able to assemble a force more than
twice the size of the Prince’s, who now became
desperate to locate and link up with Lancaster’s
army. On the 7th of September, the Prince’s army
reached the Loire in the suburbs of Tours, aiming
to join Lancaster who was just 70 miles away on
the north bank. However, heavy rains soon made the
swollen river impassable, and after receiving news
that John’s army was advancing towards him just
20 miles away, the Black Prince ordered a retreat,
whilst Lancaster withdrew into Brittany, leaving
the Black Prince to fend for himself. With both
armies moving south, the French had managed
to overtake and cut across the English line
of march and were now west of their enemy, near
Poitiers. It was clear that a major confrontation
was imminent, but while the Prince led about 7,000
men, King John had over 20,000 men with him.
On the 18th of September, the Prince took
up his position south-east of Poitiers. His
forces occupied a ridge of high ground, while his
flanks were protected by thick woods on one side,
with wagons from the baggage train, used
to shield his flanks further. The Prince
placed Warwick and Oxford’s division on his
left, Suffolk and Salisbury’s on his right,
whilst he commanded the centre. His longbowmen
were placed on the wings of the army. On the
morning of the 19th, King John and the French had
arrived. He formed his army into three divisions,
led by the Dauphin Charles, John’s
brother Philip the Duke of Orleans,
and himself. At 7:30am the Prince gathered his
carts and moved them in a southern direction,
as if he were retreating. The feint worked and
the French cavalry charged the English line.
This charge met with initial success as the
armoured French horses resisted the Prince’s
archers and crashed into the Anglo-Gascons.
However, after repositioning to the side,
the English archers targeted the horses behind the
front line to devastating effect, destroying the
momentum of the French assault. The cavalry that
had broken through the defences were surrounded
and cut down. The English then attacked the
exhausted French men-at-arms through the hedges
and spilt around the flanks of the French line,
forcing them to retreat after two hours of bloody
fighting. The strongest French division under King
John now began to advance. While this presented a
grave threat, the Black Prince launched a surprise
cavalry charge directly at the French line while
also sending a mounted force on a large flanking
manoeuvre to fall on the French left. A melee
ensued, with both sides taking casualties. But
then the Gascon reserve force crashed into the
French left flank, causing widespread panic in
John’s ranks. The English archers, having expended
their arrows, threw down their bows and launched
themselves into the battle. With contingents of
the French army now fleeing, the French King was
surrounded and captured by the English.
On the evening of the 19th of September,
the French dead stood at 2,500 men-at-arms,
while the king and dozens of notable lords
were captured. From the jaws of defeat,
the Black Prince had snatched an improbable and
total victory. The captured King John was treated
respectfully by the Black Prince, who waited
on his table on the evening after the battle
and praised the King’s valour and bravery. If the
central tenets of medieval chivalry were bravery
in battle and respect for one’s enemy, then at
Poitiers the Black Prince had demonstrated why he
would be remembered in history as the embodiment
of a chivalrous warrior. The Anglo-Gascon army
returned to Bordeaux on the 5th of October, to
great public jubilation. Thereafter a two-year
truce with the captive King John was agreed on
the 23rd of March 1357. The Prince and his royal
prisoner set sail for England and on the 24th
of May Edward of Woodstock rode through London
in triumph. This was the pinnacle of his career as
England’s warrior-prince. On the 8th of May 1358,
Edward III signed an agreement with John II, in
which John agreed to pay 4 million French crowns
for his release and recognised Edward as sovereign
ruler of the large southern province of Aquitaine.
In return Edward would renounce his claim to
the French throne. This treaty constituted a
substantial victory for the English.
Following his victory, the Prince fell back
into his ever-persistent problem of excessive
spending as he embarked on an ambitious expansion
of his Vale Royal residence in Cheshire, an
Abbey begun by his great-grandfather, Edward I.
Nevertheless, when the French provisional
government rejected the treaty signed with John,
the Black Prince and his father once again
led a large expedition into France on the
28th October 1359, intending to march on Rheims
and have Edward III crowned as King of France.
However, the army failed to capture the
city and Edward decided to negotiate,
agreeing to the Treaty of Bretigny on the 8th
of May 1360. Under the terms of the treaty,
Edward ceded lands in the north and west of France
totalling around a third of the country. In return
Edward relinquished his claim to the French throne
and lowered John’s ransom to 3 million crowns.
With the war with France now briefly in abeyance,
the 31 year-old Black Prince married Joan of Kent,
his 33-year-old cousin, in the summer of 1361. He
returned to France and soon after he was invested
as Prince of Aquitaine as a reward for his victory
at Poitiers. The Prince departed for France
with most of his household, as well as over 600
soldiers, arriving at Lormont near Bordeaux on the
29th of June. There the Prince was quite popular
at the beginning of his rule, as his exceedingly
generous hospitality and grand feasts endeared him
to the local lords. Furthermore, the Prince and
his wife were extremely happy in their new domain,
especially so upon the birth of their first child
in January 1365, a son whom they named Edward.
In addition, in a meeting of the three estates,
the representative body of Aquitaine, in September
1365, the Prince showed himself to be willing to
listen to the grievances of his subjects, and act
to redress them, working to reduce lawlessness
in his lands, after hearing complaints of
marauding brigands and feuding lords. Meanwhile,
France had a new king. John II had died in April
1364. The new king, Charles V, proved himself to
be a strong and effective ruler, and a formidable
adversary for the Black Prince, who by 1365 was
already experiencing some tension with his nobles,
including his old enemy, the Count of Armagnac.
The Black Prince’s attention was soon drawn
away from Aquitaine altogether towards Spain,
when he received a message in 1366 from the
displaced King Pedro of Castile begging the
Prince to help restore him to the throne. The 32
year-old Pedro had succeeded his father, Alfonso
XI, as the sole child of a loveless marriage to
Queen Maria of Portugal, but his father preferred
his mistress Leonore de Guzman, with whom he had
multiple children who he showered with honour and
affection, whilst isolating Pedro, who forged
a strong resentment towards his half-siblings,
especially the eldest, Enrique of Trastamara. As
King, Pedro was a valuable ally of Edward III,
as Castile had emerged as the most powerful state
in the Iberian peninsula. Then, in 1366, Pedro
was removed from the throne by his bitter enemy
Enrique, in an invasion supported by Charles V of
France. When he fled to Gascony, many of the Black
Prince’s advisors were opposed to helping Pedro,
as in his rapid flight over the Pyrenees
he had not brought any soldiers with him,
meaning that the Prince would have to mobilise an
army and bear the financial burden of the campaign
if he was to try to restore Pedro to the throne of
Castile. Furthermore, Pedro was widely considered
to be an unstable tyrant, one who had also been
excommunicated by the Catholic Church.
Despite his reservations about Pedro, the English
were wary of allowing Castile to come under French
influence and were determined to uphold the
Anglo-Castilian alliance. Therefore, Edward
reluctantly agreed to help restore the Castilian
King on September 23rd 1366, on the condition
that Pedro swear an oath to reform how he ruled if
he was restored to power in Castile, and to also
repair his relations with the church. After the
birth, on the 6th of January 1367, of the Black
Prince’s second son, Richard, who would later
become King Richard II of England, the Prince left
Bordeaux to join his assembling army of over 6,000
men in the foothills of the Pyrenees. Then, on the
14th of February 1367, the Prince’s vanguard
under Sir John Chandos, crossed the Pyrenees,
followed on the 20th by the Prince, with the main
body, reaching Pamplona, the capital of Navarre
on the 23rd of February. As the Prince’s army
reached Vitoria it suffered under harsh weather
and a lack of provisions. While encamped around
Vitoria it was ambushed on the 25th of March by
a Franco-Castilian force under Enrique, losing
hundreds of men. However, this shock spurred
the Prince into action, and after retreating
into Navarre he marched south on a new route.
On the 3rd of April 1367, the two armies would
meet on an open plain a mile east of the town of
Najera. Though the exact sizes of the armies are
disputed, it is likely that Enrique of Trastamara,
held the numerical advantage, but the Black Prince
had the element of surprise. He shielded his
advance behind a ridge and appeared unexpectedly
with his army on Enrique’s left flank.
The surprised Castilians and French launched
a poorly coordinated cavalry charge,
which was shot down by the Anglo-Gascon archers.
Enrique’s Spanish soldiers were not accustomed
to the devastating effectiveness of the English
longbow, which broke the advancing infantry in
similar fashion and the Prince, seeing the
enemy’s distress, charged with his mounted
soldiers to rout the Spanish and French troops.
The Battle of Najera was another complete victory
for the Black Prince, whose army inflicted heavy
casualties on the Spanish, whilst sustaining very
few casualties themselves, much to the delight
of Edward III. Despite this, the Black Prince was
soon frustrated to learn that Enrique had escaped
to France, to be shielded by Charles V. On the 2nd
of May at Burgos, Pedro was informed that the
campaign to restore him to his throne had cost
over £400,000 and that the English crown expected
to be reimbursed. Although Edward intended to
remain with his army in Spain to ensure the debt
was paid, an outbreak of dysentery hit the army in
August. It was almost certainly at this time that
the Prince himself was struck with the sickness,
from which he would never fully recover. As the
disease spread, the Anglo-Gascons marched back
across the Pyrenees and returned to Bordeaux in
early September 1367. By autumn of 1367, Pedro’s
failure to repay his debts left the Black Prince
on the verge of bankruptcy, with most of his army
still unpaid. The Prince was accordingly forced to
resort to taxing Aquitaine, introducing a property
tax known as the fouage, which was approved by
the estates in January 1368. A cohort of noblemen,
led by the ever-difficult Count of Armagnac,
denounced the tax as oppressive, and refused
to allow its collection on their lands.
Following his Spanish expedition, many of the
Prince’s political strengths were fading, as
he now lacked the financial means to maintain
loyalty through his generosity and gift giving,
and his personal charm was greatly diminished by
debilitating sickness, which continually plagued
him from the summer of 1368. In June of that year,
Charles saw his opportunity and took it, entering
an agreement with Armagnac, Albret and the Count
of Perigord, three influential Aquitanian nobles
who were resentful of the Prince and his new tax,
pledging to defend them if the Prince ever
attacked their domains and granted them lands
and funds, whilst the nobles promised to fight for
Charles to recover Aquitaine for the French crown.
As the Prince’s health worsened, his hold over
Aquitaine became ever more precarious. Edward III,
whose energy and decisiveness had declined
with age and ill health, failed to provide
the Prince with adequate financial resources,
and had dithered whilst Louis, Duke of Anjou,
brother of Charles V, began raising troops
in southern France, in coordination with the
rebellious nobles, to threaten the Prince’s
authority. Furthermore, the Prince’s position
was further weakened when Enrique of Trastamara
reconquered Castile and killed Pedro in March
of 1369, placing a French ally directly south of
the Prince’s lands. In June 1369, following months
of tension, war broke out once again, between
England and France, and Edward III sent a small
force under the Earls of Cambridge and Pembroke
to assist the Black Prince. Charles, meanwhile,
had saved prudently throughout his reign, and had
large funds with which to supply the rebellious
lords, as towns and castles in vulnerable eastern
Aquitaine began to fall to the French.
As he remained crippled by illness, to add
to the Prince’s woes, he began to lose some
of his closest military companions. Sir James
Audley died of sickness at the end of August,
whilst his most experienced captain in Aquitaine,
Sir John Chandos, was killed in a skirmish in
Poitou on the 1st of January 1370. The French then
launched an offensive in the summer of 1370 with
two large armies, one of which, under Charles V’s
brother John, Duke of Berry, captured the city of
Limoges in north-eastern Aquitaine in mid-August,
after the Bishop Jean de Cros, a trusted friend
of the Black Prince, surrendered it to the French.
The Prince, aghast at the city’s surrender, joined
a 4,000-strong army and marched to Limoges in what
would be his final expedition, though he had to be
carried in a litter, as he was by now too ill to
mount a horse. Nevertheless, the army arrived and
laid siege to the city on the 14th of September.
On the 19th, the Prince’s miners succeeded
in destroying a large section of the city wall,
allowing the English troops to surge into Limoges
and push back the French defenders. The city was
pillaged and burnt by the retreating French and
advancing English, and when the Bishop of Limoges
was brought before the Prince, he was told that
he deserved execution, although he was ultimately
spared. The recovery of Limoges was an important
victory for the English, but it was clouded by the
news that the Black Prince’s eldest son, Edward,
had died from the plague just days after the fall
of Limoges. This devastating news, combined with
his own illness, made the Black Prince resolve
to leave Aquitaine and return to England.
The capture of Limoges became infamous, as
the French chronicler, Jean Froissart, wrote
an account of it in which he claimed that the
Prince’s forces indiscriminately killed a large
part of the civilian population after the city
fell. Froissart’s account was largely fabricated.
While there was substantial property damage,
casualties were limited to around 300 people,
not the 3,000 that Froissart suggested.
Nevertheless, this story of the capture
of Limoges stained the Prince’s reputation.
In early January 1371, the Prince and his
household sailed to England. He spent much of
the remainder of his life at Berkhamsted Castle,
having left his brother, John of Gaunt, in charge
of the worsening military situation in Aquitaine.
By the time a year’s truce was signed in June
1375 England’s holdings in France had been greatly
diminished. At home, old King Edward III had
become unpopular, as he came under the influence
of his young mistress, Alice Perrers. Meanwhile,
the Black Prince remained an admired figure,
though his health continued to deteriorate from
the dysentery he had contracted, an illness that
is easily treated with antibiotics today. As
the Prince approached his 46th year in 1376,
he was virtually unable to leave his bed, and on
the 1st of June he was carried to the Palace of
Westminster so that he could spend the last of
his days with his elderly father and the rest
of his family. On Sunday the 8th of June 1376,
Edward of Woodstock said a final prayer and died,
almost certainly from the dysentery that had
plagued him since the Spanish campaign nine
years earlier. He was then buried in Canterbury
Cathedral, where his tomb can still be seen today.
Just over a year later, his father died, meaning
that the Black Prince’s 10-year old son, Richard,
became England’s first new king in half
a century. Richard II would prove to be a
divisive ruler who was deposed in 1399 in what
many historians view as the start of the Wars
of the Roses that tore England apart between the
1450s and the ascent of the Tudors in 1485.
The Black Prince is regarded as one of the
greatest medieval warriors in the history of
England, playing a leading role in two of the most
decisive English victories of the Hundred Years’
War at Crecy and Poitiers. He was respected by
the people of England throughout his life and by
his friends and soldiers, whom he never ceased
to reward generously for their service to him.
Even the French Kings, John II and Charles V,
recognised the Prince’s valour and honour. The
Prince’s reputation has significant blemishes
however, especially in France where his brutal
raids through Languedoc and northern Aquitaine,
prior to the battle of Poitiers included mass
atrocities towards civilians and the destruction
of significant swathes of French countryside.
Nevertheless, the Black Prince was
above all else a hero for his time,
labelled by his surgeon John Arderne,
who accompanied him on many campaigns,
as “the very flower of chivalry”, for there
are few men in history who embodied medieval
chivalry as much as Edward of Woodstock did.
The principles of courage in battle and showing
honour towards one’s opponents defined the
warrior-Prince’s life, who lived and died
adhering to a code of chivalry that was widely
aspired to in medieval Europe. Chivalry in many
ways defined the era of the Black Prince, and the
Black Prince in many ways defined chivalry.
What do you think of the Black Prince? Was he a
ruthless military commander who devastated large
parts of France through his chevauchée raids,
or would he have made a great English king?
Please let us know in the comment section and in
the meantime thank you very much for watching.